hi my name is Joe Brewer and I'm a
change strategist today I want to
continue with my series of book reviews
on material that I think are helpful for
people that want to create large scale
social change the book that I'm
reviewing today is the Emperor of all
maladies a biography of cancer by
Siddhartha Mukherjee and this is a book
that paints the history it tells the
story of how cancer research began in
the early history of human civilization
and the earliest recorded cases back in
ancient Egypt all the way through the
medical discoveries of the last few
centuries and especially in the last 100
years up to the present and the reason
that this book is so important for those
of us that want to create social change
is that it goes through and explores how
ideas can compete with each other within
different groups of people and how the
competitions between those different
activities can lead to progress and in
this case the book focusing on cancer
helps us understand the relationship
between say the advances in surgical
procedures and the power dynamics of a
surgeon's as very important people in
powerful people in medical institutions
and say the late nineteenth and early
twentieth centuries and then new
technological and scientific discoveries
associated with genetics and
pharmaceuticals that led to chemotherapy
and then later hormone therapy for
dealing with cancer and one thing that I
really loved about this book is that
even as a dealt with this really
difficult and somewhat depressing topic
of cancer and the hardships and how
difficult it was for people to survive
when they were diagnosed with cancer and
a lot of the book focuses on leukemia
and cancer and children which is a
difficult topic to study but as you go
through and read the history of how far
we've come and how much we now
understand and also specifically the
ways that the advances were made it
actually is quite an inspiring and
hopeful story so for example we now are
in a place where the complexity of our
approach to treating cancer
is on par with the complexity of cancer
itself meaning that it's becoming a
tractable problem and something that
while we may never get rid of cancer
entirely it's becoming much more at a
treatable type of disease or category of
many diseases that we now deal with on a
regular basis and so what I love about
this book is it shows us how to
understand the way that advances can be
made in really complex issues how much
progress can be made in just a few
decades and also the interplay of
institutional cultural and technological
changes can all come together and
converge to solve really difficult
problems so if you're interested in
understanding how cultural systems can
evolve in time where there are very
difficult problems with direct human
consequences and how progress can be
made over a span of time through
collaboration institution building
policy design science and policy and our
interactions and a passion and
dedication of individual people then
this is really a wonderful book to read
and of course it did when a pure appeal
it surprised and it's quite widely read
already but I want to suggest that it
should be part of the toolkit for people
that are trying to create large scale
social change so that's it go out and
get the Emperor of all maladies if you
want to understand how cultural
evolution can guide the solving of very
difficult problems in society and um you
know let me know what you think alright
thanks a lot